John "Jack" M. Chapel

in john-jack-chapel | ⊕ jackchapel.com | ✓ chapel@usc.edu

Summary

I am an applied microeconomist with a decade of experience conducting social science research in academic and public sector settings. I enjoy collaborating with multidisciplinary teams, working on a diverse portfolio of projects, and implementing causal inference research designs to inform program and policy improvements.

Fields of Interest: Applied Microeconomics, Health, Labor, Urban, Public Policy Citizenship: U.S.

EDUCATION

Ph.D., Economics, University of Southern California	2019-2024
M.A., Economics, University of Southern California	2019 – 2021
B.S., Economics (with distinction), Tulane University	2011 - 2015

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

U.S. Department of Labor, Chief Evaluation Office

Summer Fellow (via Manhattan Strategy Group)

2023

University of Southern California, Schaeffer Center for Health Policy & Economics

Research Assistant for Bryan Tysinger, Director of Health Policy Microsimulation

2020-2023

University of Southern California, Center for Economic & Social Research

Research Assistant for Silvia H. Barcellos, Associate Professor

2022-2023

Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Division for Heart Disease and Stroke Prevention

Research Fellow (via ORISE), Applied Research and Evaluation Branch

2015-2019

Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Office on Smoking and Health

Research Fellow (via ORISE), Evaluation and Economics teams

2015-2019

Updated: May 13, 2024

ICF International

Summer Intern, Public Health Division	2013
Summer Intern, Public Health Division	2012

RESEARCH

In-Progress and Working Papers

Distant Friends with Benefits: Social Spillover Effects from Out-of-State Medicaid Expansions

The Great Migration's Impact on Southern Inequality (with Yi-Ju Hung)

Hidden Hypertension and the Labor Force Participation of Older Americans

Peer-Reviewed Publications

Chapel JM, Tysinger B, Goldman DP, Rowe JW. The Forgotten Middle: Worsening health and economic trends extend to Americans with Modest Resources Nearing Retirement. *Health Affairs*. 2023;42(9):1230-1240.

Shantharam SS, Mahalingam M, Rasool A, Reynolds JA, Bhuiya AR, Satchell TD, **Chapel JM**, Hawkins NA, Jones CD, Jacob V, Hopkins DP. Systematic Review of Patient Characteristics, Intervention Features, and Cost of Self-Measured Blood Pressure Monitoring Interventions with Support. *American Journal of Preventive Medicine*. 2022;62(2):285-298.

- MacLeod KE, Chapel JM, McCurdy M, et al. The Implementation Cost of a Safety-Net Hospital Program Addressing Social Needs in Atlanta. *Health Services Research*. 2021;56(3):474-485.
- Hawkins NA, Bhuiya A, Shantharam S, Chapel JM, et al. A Replicable Approach to Promoting Effective Practices: Translating Cardiovascular Disease Prevention Research. *Journal of Public Health Management and Practice*. 2020;27(2):109-116.
- Zhang D, Ritchey M, Park C, Li J, **Chapel J**, Wang G. Association Between Medicaid Coverage and Income Status on Health Care Use and Costs Among Hypertensive Adults After Enactment of the Affordable Care Act. *American Journal of Hypertension*. 2019;32(10):1030-1038.
- Chapel JM & Wang G. Understanding Cost Data Collection Tools to Improve Economic Evaluations of Health Interventions. Stroke and Vascular Neurology. 2019;4(4).
- Yarnoff B, Khavjou O, Elmi J, Lowe-Beasley K, Bradley C, Amoozegar J, Wachtmeister D, Tzeng J, Chapel JM, Teixeira-Poit S, The Paul Coverdell National Acute Stroke Program Team. Estimating the Costs of Implementing Components of Stroke Systems of Care and Data-Driven Quality Improvement in the Paul Coverdell National Acute Stroke Program. *Preventing Chronic Disease*. 2019;16:190061.
- Chapel JM, Ritchey MD, Zhang D, Wang G. Prevalence and Medical Costs of Chronic Diseases Among Adult Medicaid Beneficiaries. *American Journal of Preventive Medicine*. 2017;53(6 Suppl 2):S143-S154.

Presentations, Media, and Other Publications

Conferences and Invited Presentations: (* = coauthor, \dagger = poster)

- 2023: California State University-Long Beach Economics Seminar, USC Applied Microeconomics Seminar, ACAP Social Determinants of Health Learning Collaborative
- 2022: Aging Society Research Network Annual Meeting
- 2021: International Microsimulation Association World Congress (2)
- 2020: Academy Health Annual Research Meeting*, Aging Society Research Network Annual Meeting*
- 2019: American Public Health Association*, Annual Conference on the Science of Dissemination and Implementation in Health*, Society for Applied Anthropology Annual Meeting*, Society for Prevention Research Annual Meeting†
- 2018: CDC Evaluation Day
- 2017: Academy Health Annual Research Meeting[†], Annual Conference on the Science of Dissemination and Implementation in Health*[†], Art & Science of Health Promotion Conference*
- 2016: QCOR* \dagger

Media:

Podcasts: A Health Podyssey (September 2023)

Reports: (* = coauthored)

- "Economic Evaluation: Intervention Cost Analysis in Public Health" (2018) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA.
- "Best Practices for Cardiovascular Disease Prevention Programs: A Guide to Effective Health Care System Interventions and Community Programs Linked to Clinical Services" (2017) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA.*
- "What Could Be Addressed in an Evidence-Informed State Workplace Health Promotion Law?" (2017) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA.*
- "The Shands Jacksonville Patient-Centered Medical Home Diabetes and Hypertension Self-Management Education Model: Program Costs Summary" (2016) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA.

"From Policy to Implementation: Collaborative Drug Therapy Management in an Independent Pharmacy" (2016) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA.

"Science-in-Brief synopsis of Do State Community Health Worker Laws Align with Best Available Evidence?" (2016) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA.

Honors & Awards

University of Southern California PhD Academy Scholarship and Research Fund small grant; Dornsife/graduate

school fellowship (2 years)

Centers for Disease Control CDC/ATSDR Honor Award for Excellence in Program or Policy Evaluation

(nominated with coauthors)

Tulane University Cum Laude; Dean's List; annual merit-based scholarship

Professional Activities

Teaching: CDC DHDSP 2019 Grantee Workshop, CDC DHDSP Evaluation Coffee Break Webinars, CDC

DHDSP 5-Part Webcast on the Basics of Economic Evaluation, Polygence Tutoring

Referee Service: BMC Health Services Research, Public Health Nutrition, INQUIRY: The Journal of Health Care

Organization, Provision, and Financing

Affiliations: American Society of Health Economists, American Economic Association

SKILLS

Software: Stata, ArcGIS, Matlab, NVivo, Microsoft Office suite (Word, Excel, Powerpoint)

Programming: Stata, Python, LaTex, Linux, SQL

Graduate coursework: Applied Econometrics for Program & Policy Evaluation, Big Data Econometrics, Health

Economics, Empirical Analysis of Economic Development, Urban Economics, Industrial Organization, Microeconomics, Macroeconomics, Econometrics, Probability & Statistics,

Political Economy (audit), Labor Economics (audit)

References

Prof. Jeffrey Weaver Prof. Matthew Kahn

University of Southern California University of Southern California

⊠ jbweaver@usc.edu ⊠ kahnme@usc.edu

Prof. Silvia H. Barcellos Prof. Bryan Tysinger

University of Southern California University of Southern California

⊠ sbarcell@usc.edu ⊠ btysinge@usc.edu